So here I have set up a grid that now is using six boxes,
أعددت شبكة وأنشأت بها ستة صناديق،
which we can see spread out across here.
نلاحظ هنا كيف تتوزع على امتداد الشبكة.
But as we see they are spread out in this funny way where it looks like
ولكنها تتوزع بشكل غريب، حيث
the first box and the second box have plenty of room.
يحتل الصندوقان الأول والثاني مساحة كبيرة.
Then we start squishing these boxes in here.
فيما تتكدس الصناديق المتبقية وتنضغط هنا.
To understand this behavior,
لفهم سبب هذا الأمر،
we can look at the code.
ننظر إلى البرمجية.
Here in grid-template-rows, I've set the first row to be 350 pixels.
بالنظر إلى ضبط صف قالب الشبكة، نجد أن الصف الأول ضُبط ليكون 350 بيكسل.
The second row to be 350 pixels.
والصف الثاني 350 بيكسل.
Then the third row, I'm using 1fr.
وعند الصف الثالث، استخدمت (1fr).
It denotes taking up the rest of the available space.
وهي تدل على احتلال ما تبقى من المساحة المتاحة.
So the available space is figured out by taking
يمكن معرفة المساحة المتاحة عن طريق حساب
the height of your container which I've set to a 100 view port height,
ارتفاع الحاوية، والذي ضبطته بقيمة 100 لارتفاع إطار العرض،
subtracting from it the space you've already used which would
ونطرح منه المساحة المستخدمة بالفعل، والتي ستكون
be anything in a row and the grid gap.
بأي قيمة في الصف وفي فراغ الشبكة.
Then 1fr is leaving room for anything else.
بعد ذلك تترك وحدة (1fr) مساحة لأي شيء آخر.
So after we've taken up all of our 350 pixels, our 350 pixels,
فبعد أن استخدمنا مساحة 350 بيكسل هنا، و350 بيكسل
and our grid gap twice at 15px,
ومساحة فراغ الشبكة بواقع 15 بيكسل مرتين،
it smushes the rest of it into our last row,
نضغط كل ما تبقى في الصف الأخير،
which is why we can see here it starts to smush at the bottom.
ولهذا نلاحظ تكدسها هنا في الأسفل.
But 1fr can not be used more than once.
ولكن لا يمكن استخدام وحدة الكسر (1fr) أكثر من مرة.
I could split it up and I could say I want it to be 350 pixels,
يمكن تقسيمها والقول أنني أريدها أن تكون 350 بيكسل،
350 pixels, and then twice to go through and split up the space evenly.
350 بيكسل، ثم جزئين من المساحة المتبقية ثم تقسيم ما تبقى بالتساوي.
Now it would look like this.
عندئذ ستبدو هكذا.
But get this, we don't need to use pixels at all.
ولكن، يمكننا الاستغناء عن استخدام البيكسل نهائيًا
Here I'm setting up columns,
سنضبط الأعمدة على
seven columns that each use 1fr: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7.
سبعة أعمدة يستخدم كل منها (1fr): 1,2,3,4,5,6,7.
I'm going to take away the seventh because now we only have six elements.
سأحذف السابع لأن لدينا ستة عناصر فقط.
But this is saying to divide up evenly 1fr for each of them, the columns.
تعني هذه التعليمات تقسيم المساحة بالتساوي بواقع (1fr) لكل عمود
So here we can see now we have six equal columns coming across our boxes.
نلاحظ أن لدينا ستة أعمدة متساوية تمر عبر الصناديق.
Let's make the background a little darker to make it easier to see.
لنصبح الأمور أوضح، سنجعل الخلفية بلون داكن
My favorite hex value in the world, 444.
القيمة اللونية المفضلة لدي دومًا هي 444.
We'll make the color,
لنحدد اللون،
this is from Edward Tufte's suggestion of fffff8;
هذا مستمد من اقتراح إدوارد تافت بقيمة fffff8،
which is slightly off white.
وهو لون قريب من الأبيض العاجي.
Let's make it a little easier to see with a bigger font size.
لتبدو الكتابة أوضح سنكبر حجم الخط.
Now we can see our columns spread evenly.
يمكننا أن نرى الأعمدة موزعة بشكل متساو.
But, let's be honest,
ولكن بصراحة،
going through and writing 1fr six times is a lot of work.
سيكون مرهقًا كتابة (1fr) ست مرات.
Programming is supposed to automate a lot of our work for us.
من المفترض أن تساعدنا البرمجة في أتمتة الكثير من أعمالنا.
This is where the repeat function comes in.
هنا يأتي دور وظيفة التكرار.
These two lines of code do the exact same thing.
هذان السطران من البرمجية متطابقان تمامًا.
I'll prove it to you. Let's comment out this and we'll leave our repeat function.
سأثبت لكم ذلك. لنحذف هذا وننتقل إلى وظيفة التكرار.
It's seven when we want it to be six remember.
لاحظوا هذه سبعة ولكننا نريد تغييرها إلى ستة.
Now we have six boxes spread out evenly by using repeat.
لدينا الآن ستة صناديق موزعة بالتساوي باستخدام وظيفة التكرار.
Repeat, it takes the number of times we want it to repeat
التكرار (repeat) تأخذ عدد مرات التكرار التي نريدها
which is six for us because we have six elements and then the size.
وهي ستة هنا لأن لدينا ستة عناصر، ثم الحجم.
So I'm saying repeat 1fr which means the rest of the available space six times.
وتعني أمر تكرار بوحدة (1fr)، أي الجزء المتبقي من المساحة المتاحة ست مرات.
I could also use repeat with pixels,
ويمكننا استخدام التكرار مع البيكسل،
25 pixels is pretty small.
نضع 25 بيكسل وهي مساحة صغيرة.
But you can see I've repeated six times the column.
كما ترون تكررت ست مرات في العمود.
Let's do something that looks a tiny bit less bizarre.
لنغير قيمة البيكسل لتبدو أفضل.
So by using repeat,
إذًا، يمكننا باستخدام وظيفة التكرار
we can automate the creation of our grid-template-columns.
أتمتة إنشاء أعمدة قالب الشبكة.
Now, let's talk about rows.
لننقل إلى الحديث عن الصفوف.
If you think about it when you're doing web development,
عند تطوير صفحة الويب،
there's oftentimes where you're going to want
كثيرًا ما نواجه حالات نحتاج فيها
an infinite number of rows or as many rows as there is content.
عددًا لا نهائيًا من الصفوف أو عدد صفوف يتناسب مع حجم المحتوى.
Think about the way a Facebook feed works.
لنأخذ مثلًا صفحة الفيسبوك.
You just continue to go down and down and down.
فنحن نواصل التصفح بالانتقال نحو الأسفل دون توقف.
So it's not like you're setting the number of rows initially,
في هذه الحالة لا يمكن تحديد عدد الصفوف في البداية،
the number of rows need to develop from the amount of content you have.
فعدد الصفوف يتطور وفقًا لحجم المحتوى الموجود لديك.
Luckily for us, CSS grid makes this fairly easy with the grid-auto-rows syntax.
تُسهّل علينا ذلك شبكة CSS من خلال تركيب الصفوف التلقائية في الشبكة.
Grid-auto-rows replaces grid-template-rows. In this instance,
تحل الصفوف التلقائية في الشبكة محل صفوف قالب الشبكة. في هذه الحالة،
we're going to use grid-auto-rows with minmax.
نستخدم صفوف التلقائية في الشبكة باستخدام الأمر مينماكس
Now minmax works similarly to repeat.
تعمل وظيفة مينماكس بشكل مماثل للتكرار.
Repeat took two values,
التكرار يأخذ قيمتين،
minmax takes two values.
ووظيفة مينماكس تأخذ قيمتين.
The first is a minimum value that each row must be.
الأولى هي أدنى قيمة لكل صف.
So this is saying that each row has to be at least 100 pixels and at most is auto.
وهذا يعني أن كل صف يجب أن يكون 100 بيكسل على الأقل، ويزداد تلقائيًا كحد أقصى.
So what auto will do is auto will let it be as big as its content holds.
تتيح القيمة تلقائيًا للصف أن يكبر حجمه بما يتناسب مع حجم المحتوى.
So if we have giant letters,
بالتالي، إن كانت لدينا أحرف ضخمة
then it'll be a much taller row.
سيكون ارتفاع الصفوف أكبر بكثير.
But they have to be at least 100 pixels.
ولكن، يجب أن تكون 100 بيكسل على الأقل.
Let's take a look at what this looks like in our code.
لنلق نظرة كيف سيبدو ذلك في الصفحة.
So here we can see now that we have very very evenly made rows just by using minmax.
نلاحظ أن استخدام مينماكس أعطانا صفوفًا متساوية.
So now let's try to put together the grid-auto-rows using
لنجرب استخدام الصفوف التلقائية في الشبكة باستخدام
minmax and grid-template-columns using 1fr.
مينماكس وأعمدة قالب الشبكة باستخدام (1fr)
We've set up our columns to have two columns each of
ضبطنا الأعمدة لتحتوي على عمودين، يحتل كل منهما
them taking up half of the available space left,
نصف المساحة المتاحة المتبقية،
and we've set up our rows to be as many rows as we need to fit
وضبطنا الصفوف لتحتوي على عدد الصفوف التي نحتاجها
each element in the two columns between 50 pixels and 135 pixels.
ليتسع كل صف لعنصر في عمودين على أن يكون ارتفاعه ما بين 50 بيكسل و 135 بيكسل.
So what would happen if we added another column?
ماذا سيحدث إن أضفنا عمودًا آخر؟
We can see that it adjusts perfectly.
نلاحظ أنها تتغير وتنضبط بشكل مثالي.
So now we have three columns and two rows.
لدينا الآن ثلاثة أعمدة وصفّين.
We could continue doing this or we could try using repeat,
يمكننا تكرار ذلك أو استخدام وظيفة التكرار
let's say 4, 1fr.
لنضع 4 و(1fr)
Now we can see that it has gone into four columns and the boxes adjust accordingly.
نلاحظ أنها أصبحت أربعة أعمدة، وتوزّعت الصناديق وفقًا لذلك.
This is an example of how you can use minmax with grid-auto-rows and
كان هذا مثالًا على كيفية استخدام مينماكس مع الصفوف التلقائية في الشبكة،
repeat with columns to create fancy auto magic grids.
ووظيفة التكرار مع الأعمدة لإنشاء شبكات تلقائية بيسر.
Good luck doing this on your own. I believe in you.
أتمنى لكم التوفيق في تجربة ذلك وحدكم. أثق بقدرتكم على ذلك.